All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, good ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. Today's
דף Daf is ס, Samech, 60. We pick up with about ten
lines from the bottom on נט עמוד ב, Nun Tet Amud Bet,
ומיניקת בנו. Umeneket Beno. So one of the tasks or duties of
a wife to the husband in addition to the other types of
domestic chores is to nurse the child, her child, not if he
has one from another wife. So the גמרא Gemara says the following.
לימא מתניתין דלא כבית שמאי. Leima Matnitin De-lo Ke-Beit Shammai. Let our
משנה Mishnah not be like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. דתניא, De-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, נדרה שלא להניק. Nadra Shelo Lehanch. She
made a vow that prevents her from nursing the child. Now what
type of a vow can she make? It's not a שבועה. Shevuah.
Remember a vow makes something forbidden on a person. So it could
either be that she makes the benefit of her nursing forbidden to
her husband and then her husband benefits indirectly from, you know, from
it because his son is being nursed. Or she makes it forbidden
on herself and the גמרא Gemara discusses that. גמרא Gemara says that
a woman derives benefit, you know, just in the act of nursing.
It's a, you know, it's a pleasurable act for the mother. And
so she makes some type of a vow that prevents either her
or him from nursing the child, from doing the act of that
forbids the nursing done to him or her which prevents her from
doing the nurse. So what's the הלכה? Halakha? בית שמאי אומרים שומטת
דד מפיו. Beit Shammai Omerim Shomtet Dad Mi-pi.
She removes the breast from the kid's mouth, meaning it doesn't matter
if she's in the middle of nursing, she stops nursing. Okay, בית
הלל אומרים, Beit Hillel Omerim, בית הלל Beit Hillel says, כופוה ומיניקת
אותו. Kofo Umeneket Oto. The husband can force her to nurse the
child. Now which means what? Is she violating the vow? Presumably what
it means is is that like we saw before about the אישות,
Ishut, about forbidding the מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim and so on, that
since she, since the husband she owes that service or the husband
has a lien on her however you want to say to the
husband, she is not in a position to make that forbidden. She
is not and therefore the vow was not binding. But בית שמאי
Beit Shammai feels that the vow is binding. So it seems like
according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai she doesn't have a legal responsibility
to nurse the child. נתגרשה, Nishreshah, now once she's divorced, אינה כופוה,
Ena Kofah, he cannot force her because now she has no obligation
to him and then presumably the vow takes effect. That gets to
our discussion earlier about a vow taking effect at a postponed time.
ואם היה מכירה, Ve-im Hayah Makira, now if the child already recognized
the mother and therefore רש"י Rashi says not just recognized her but
will not nurse from another mother, from another, you know, from a
nursemaid, recognizes her and will only nurse from the mother. In this
case, נותן לה שכרה, Notin Lah Secharah, and even though she's not,
she no longer has a financial or legal obligation, but there's the
reality that the kid needs to nurse from his mother. So therefore
he pays her her fee, whatever the nursemaid fee would be, וכופוה
ומיניקת אותו, Ve-kofo Umeneket Oto, and he can force her, his ex-wife,
to nurse the child. So that's interesting because obviously you understand how
important it is to the health of the child now in terms
of, you know, being nursed by the mother. But is the woman
now violating the vow? You know, that's another interesting question, right? Because
now it seems like the vow is binding or maybe it doesn't
mean that. Maybe it just means that it's a different discussion. Not
with a vow. Maybe it's just talking about one scenario is a
vow. There's another scenario that he divorced his wife. And if he
divorced her he can't force her to nurse the child, but if
the child needs his mother, then he can. Okay, but if we're
still talking about the scenario about the vow, what's happening? Is she
violating the vow? I mean, maybe. Maybe we consider פיקוח נפש. Pikuach
Nefesh. It's a very important question that always comes up about, you
know, nursing mothers and יום כיפור Yom Kippur and other types of
issues and expressing milk on שבת Shabbat and how much are the
nurse is mother's milk and the mother's nursing for a child considered
פיקוח נפש. Pikuach Nefesh. So maybe, although then it would be funny
that we don't talk about trying to encourage her to annul the
vow, right? To go to a היתר Heter of the נדר. Neder.
So maybe what it's saying is is that in a scenario where
the child still needs the mother to nurse, maybe she, and therefore
it's a scenario where the husband is still legally entitled to force
her to nurse, although with payment, so maybe in that case the
vow wasn't binding all together even during the period of divorce. Right?
You understand what I'm saying? Rather than saying the vow is binding
and he's forcing her to nurse, maybe since it's a case where
he could force her to nurse, the vow never even became binding
for that period. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't really explore that. Anyway
it's clear that according to בית הלל Beit Hillel she generally has
a responsibility and number two once the child needs specifically the mother,
it's not exactly clear where that responsibility is coming from, is it
a general, you know, פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, חז"ל Chazal are requiring
her, but somehow she becomes required although she can be paid for
to nurse her child. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says, so
it seems like our משנה Mishnah is not בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
It seems like בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't have this responsibility.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
מפני הסכנה. Mipnei hasakanah. I'm sorry that's the last line. He'd force
her to nurse the child because of the danger to the child.
The very important two words which I didn't read before which is
again the recognizing that mother's milk and nursing is considered a סכנה
Sakanah for the child. So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו תימא בית
שמאי. Afilu Teima Beit Shammai. It could even be going according to
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha Bemai Askinan what are
we talking about? כגון שנדרה היא וקיים לה הוא. Kigon Shenadra Hi
Vekiyam Lah Hu. She made the vow and he upheld it. She
made the vow but he not just did he not passively not
annul it, he actively was מקיים mekayem it. Once the husband says
I accept that vow, then even on the same day he can
no longer annul it. So he
actively sort of affirmed the vow. So now the question is, so
the vow is binding, who's to blame for this? Is she to
blame because she made it, or is he to blame because he
affirmed it? So דקסבר בית שמאי, de-kasavar Beis Shammai, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai holds, הוא נותן אצבע בין שיניה, hu nosein etzba bein shineha,
he was the guy who poked her in the teeth. Interesting touch
where right coming up to the סדר, Seder, right, אף אתה הקהה
את שיניו, af ata hakeih es shinav, blunting the teeth, have that
same imagery of the sort of hitting the teeth. Okay. So he's
to blame. ובית הלל סברי, u-Beis Hillel savri, היא נותנה אצבע בין
שיניה, hi nosna etzba bein shineha, she put her finger between her
teeth. Maybe also you're stopping up the, no, you're stopping up the
teeth of the child, not her teeth. Anyway. Okay. Anyway, she's to
blame. She made the vow. Okay. So therefore what are they debating?
What they're really debating is everybody agrees that the vow is, so
therefore it's not therefore clear though, even if it's a question of
blame, what does that have to do with whether she can force
her to feed, right, you know, how does that relate to the
question of whether the vow is binding and can you force her
to feed or not? So תוספות Tosafos says in this scenario, we're
assuming that when בית הלל Beis Hillel says force her to feed,
he doesn't literally mean force her to feed. It means everybody would
agree that the vow was binding, but the question would be whether
she now has to pay for hiring a nursemaid. If he's to
blame, then she doesn't have to pay. And if she's considered to
be blame, then she does have to pay. So read this way,
it's not a question of does she have an obligation and is
the vow binding? Read this way, who's to blame and who pays?
Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. But the גמרא Gemara
says no, if that's true, וניפלגו בכתובה בעלמא, veniflegu bi-Kesuva ba'alma, why
specifically debate the case of nursing? Just have a general debate of
if a woman takes a vow that prevents her from fulfilling her
כתובה Kesuva obligations and the husband affirms it, whose fault, who's to
blame, is he to blame or her to blame? And the נפקא
מינה nafka mina would be if he, when he divorces her, because
you can't live together if those tasks can't be done, he'll divorce
her, but does he have to pay the כתובה Kesuva or not?
If she's to blame, then he doesn't pay the כתובה. Kesuva. If
he's to blame, then he does. So that can't be the debate.
ועוד תניא, ve-od tanya, we've taught explicitly in a ברייתא, Baraisa, בית
שמאי אומרים אינה מניקה, Beis Shammai omrim eina menika, that she does
not have to nurse the child.
אלא מחוורתא כסיסין דלא כבית שמאי. ela mehavarta kesisin d'lo ke-Beis Shammai.
It really shows you what a completely radically different society there is
that you could suggest that of all the tasks that a mother
has to do, a wife has to do, nursing the child is
not one of them. Of course, if you go back twenty, thirty
years, you know, when our, you know, for my parents or whatever,
there was a whole kind of wisdom was that it's better to
give formula than to nurse. So in their days maybe it was
better to, not better, but it was just standard to hire nursemaids
rather than to nurse.
Right. Exactly. So if you regularly hire nursemaids, then maybe that was
not considered a task of the mother, which is again pretty fascinating.
What?
I was allergic to milk.
You were allergic to milk. I had to... well that's interesting. I
too. Anyway, okay, so bottom line is there's a מחלוקת בית הלל
ובית שמאי machlokes Beis Hillel u-Beis Shammai about whether a child, whether
a mother is obligated to nurse the child. Again, interesting issue here
about taking a vow and about it being taken effect when she's
divorced, but being overridden, you know, what exactly that means, is the
vow really overridden? But anyway, the important principle here is that the
idea that it's סכנה sakana for the child who needs his mother's
milk and can't nurse from another from another woman. And that's very
important להלכה. le-halacha. And then the broader issue here about if a
woman takes the vow and the husband affirms it, who's to blame
in terms of who therefore has to suffer the financial consequences as
the result of that vow in terms of כתובה Kesuva and paying
the כתובה Kesuva and so on. Yes.
How do you explain the phrase נותן אצבע בין שיניה? nosein etzba
bein shineha?
That he was he's to blame. He's the one. Yes, I mean
it's just a nice colorful phrase, but he's the one you know
he's at fault. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אם היה מכירה. im haya makkira. Now we're going to look at
that ברייתא Baraisa that we just dealt with and the ברייתא Baraisa
says that if if the child recognized the mother and רש״י Rashi
adds although it's not explicit that he won't nurse from another mother
from another woman, then again she has no then she obviously must
feed the child must nurse the child.
Again, interesting although she took a vow, but maybe in that scenario
the vow would not be binding even if she's divorced and so
on. And even putting the vow aside, she's divorced, she no longer
has an obligation to nurse, but if the child already will only
nurse from her, then even after divorce she has to nurse and
the husband pays for pays her fee. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. עד כמה, ad kama, how old can we
until when do we assume that I mean it's like it's not
really עד כמה, ad kama, it's starting when. Starting when do we
assume that the child will recognize the mother and therefore not and
and the mother will have to continue to nurse him? So אמר
רבא אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב, amar Rava amar Rav
Yirmiya bar Abba amar Rav, שלושה חודשים, shlosha chodashim, once he's three
months old.
ושמואל אמר שלושים יום, u-Shmuel amar shloshim yom, thirty days. רב יצחק
אמר רבי יוחנן חמישים יום, Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan chamishim yom,
fifty days. אמר רב שימי בר חייא הלכה כ amar Rav Shimi
bar Chiya halacha ke- שאמר משום רבי יוחנן she'amar mishum Rabi Yochanan
we rule like the last one of fifty days. So now the
גמרא Gemara says בשלמא רב ורבי יוחנן bishlama Rav v'Rebi Yochanan the
debate of Rav and Yochanan three months or
fifty days כחד וחד כחורפיה, k'chad v'chad k'churfeih, each one based on
the child's
awareness. So some children will be more aware and therefore they'll recognize
after fifty days and others after three months. ושמואל u'Shmuel but Shmuel
says one month already he, child only recognizes his mother. כי האי
גוונא מי משכחת לה? ki hai gavna mi meshkachat lah? Do you
ever have such a thing? So, and the גמרא Gemara sort of
leaves it without an answer. Now, I don't know, I should've done
some research here, but I assume that children pretty soon sort of
start to- does anybody know? The answer? Here we have a room
full of men.
Who knows his mother? For sure if she's a fifty days.
My understanding is on some inchoate way immediately.
Right. So I guess the question is number one is does recognize
the mother or is there also or will only nurse from the
mother which is what רש״י Rashi adds in but that's not explicit
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. כי אתא רב דימי רמי בר יחזקאל ki ata Rav Dimi
Rami bar Yechezkel when Rav Dimi bar Yechezkel came from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אמר לא תציתו להני כללי דחיי יהודה אחי משמיה דשמואל,
amar lo tatzitu l'hani klali d'chayei Yehuda achi mishmeih d'Shmuel, don't listen
to these rules that Yehuda my brother said in the name of
שמואל, Shmuel, which is interesting because we didn't really have a רב
יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel before, but anyway presumably some
of this was given over in רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda name. הכי
אמר שמואל, hachi amar Shmuel, this is what שמואל Shmuel says. כל
זמן שמכירה, kol zman she'makira, that you do not have a rule
thirty days, fifty days, ninety days. Case by case. If you want
to force this mother to continue to nurse her child after divorce,
you have to look case by case whether the child will only
nurse from the mother or not, or whether he recognizes the mother,
the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says now we're going to
have a story about that.
ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דשמואל, hahi d'atai l'kameih d'Shmuel, a woman came in
front of שמואל Shmuel and she was a case that it was
divorced and the husband wanted her to continue to nurse the child
and she didn't want to. So אמר ליה, amar leih, again it's
so fascinating even the society that the mother doesn't want to continue
to nurse the child, but you have to understand the reality, she's
not taking the kid home with her, right? I mean the husband
is the one that has- the assumption is basically that the husband
is the one that has what do you call it custody. The
wife is being sent out of the house and even though she's
divorced and the husband's holding onto the kid, he wants her to
continue to nurse the kid and she, so she doesn't want to
do it, again, even for pay.
That's standard in divorce cases the children stay in the home of
the father.
Yes, correct. In the גמרא Gemara the standard assumption is that they're
the father's kids. Okay, that's the reality of patriarchy. Okay, so now
the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, so אתאי לקמיה דשמואל, atai l'kameih d'Shmuel, אמר
ליה לרב דימי בר יוסף זיל בדקה, amar leih l'Rav Dimi bar
Yosef zil badka, go check her, let's see if the child will
only recognize his mother. Now again to realize this רש״י Rashi said
that will only nurse from the mother. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say
that explicitly, the גמרא Gemara just says whether the kid recognizes the
mother. So go check her out. אזל אותבה בדרא דנשי azal otvah
b'dara d'neshei he went and he did a lineup like the police
lineup, so he had a lineup and then he took the kid
in front of the one-way mirror and said okay which one is
your mother?
So he put her in a line of women, קמי דרא דנשי,
kamei dara d'neshei, ושקליה לברה וקמהדרה לה
עלייהו,
v'shakleih l'breih v'kamahadrah
lah aleiyhu, a row of women, דרא dara is a row, ושקליה
לברה v'shakleih l'breih took her son וקמהדרה לה עלייהו v'kamahadrah lah aleiyhu
and had the son pass in front of the women. כי מטא
לגבה הות קמשפי לאפא ki mata lgabah havat k'masfi l'apa when it
passed in front of the
mother he would he recognized, looked in her face, in the mother's
face. So he showed some recognition.
כבשתנהו לעינה מיניה kavashtanhu l'einei mineih so she hid her eyes from
the son, she looked away. אמר לה, amar lah, so he said
to her, because she didn't want the son to recognize her because
then she'd have to continue nursing him. So he said to her,
נטוף עינך קום דרי ברך, netof einach kum dari brach, lift up
your eyes,
go carry your son and you have to now nurse him because
clearly he recognizes you. So this seems against רש״י, Rashi, this seems
that it's just a question of recognition, not a question of refusing
to nurse from other women, because there's a much easier way to
test if the kid will nurse from other women. You know how
to test if the kid will nurse from other women?
Give him to a nursemaid and see if he'll nurse from another
woman! So although רש״י Rashi inserted that, it seems here the simple
question is recognizing the mother or not. So you have to do
a lineup. Okay now the גמרא Gemara says סומא מנא ידעה suma
m'na yad'ah how would a blind child, such a tragedy thinking about
somebody who's born blind but that happens, a blind child how would
he מנא ידעה, m'na yad'ah, how would he know? So אמר רב
אשי בריחא ובטעמא amar Rav Ashi b'reicha u'v'ta'ama because taste and smell,
the other senses, he would still be able to
know- to identify. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: יונק
תינוק והולך עד עשרים וארבעה חודש. yonek tinok veholech ad esrim ve'arba'ah
chodesh. Now this גמרא, Gemara, this is like the דף daf that
is like the דף daf for everybody in the La Leche League
or whatever, you know. This all, this is the דף daf in
the גמרא. Gemara. Now we're sort of transitioning between like the white,
mother's, the wife's obligation to nurse to general statements about nursing. We've
already had one critically important one הלכה, halacha, which is the idea
that it's a סכנה sakana if the child needs to be nursed
in. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן:
tanu rabbanan: יונק תינוק והולך
עד
עשרים וארבעה חודש.
yonek tinok veholech ad esrim
ve'arba'ah chodesh. An infant can continue nursing until twenty-four months. מכאן
ואילך, mikan va'eilach, afterwards, כיונק שקץ, ke'yonek sheket, is like nursing from
a, you know, an abomination. Like it's disgusting, says this first opinion,
דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's Rabbi Eliezer says, you know,
for somebody who's already able to eat like, you know, solid food
and so on and is of a certain age, to be, you
know, to be nursing from a human being. Now the question is,
is it because it considers the place it comes from disgusting, like
mother's milk, you know, that once you're sort of, you know, any,
for anyone who's not an infant that's like, you know, anything that
comes from a human, a human byproduct is disgusting. The phrase יונק
שקץ yonek sheket seems to suggest it's not just the source of
the milk, but it's the act of nursing. After a certain age
it's not considered appropriate to be doing the act of nursing from
a mother. The נפקא מינה nafkaminah would be if the mother expressed
milk into a bottle, how would this first opinion hold of it?
And we're going to see some of that in a minute. So
everybody understands, right, this is a disapproving statement, but is it disapproving
because of the source of the milk or because of the act
of nursing? And it seems to be the act of the nursing.
And let's face it, you know, there are, you know, people that
nurse their kids, particularly women that really are very מקפיד makpid on
this, that will nurse their kids even beyond two years, three years,
four years, five years, we're about to see that. And you know,
for a lot of people, myself included, there's something that feels very
weird and wrong about that, you know, but maybe that has to
just do with our norms of society and so on. You know,
is it all cultural? Is it also because there's a, you think
that there's a sexual element at that stage, you know, that, you
know, that type of a thing, or is it just that it
seems inappropriate once the child is out of being an infant? Anyway,
that's an opinion you have here that says after two years it's
like a, it's a disgusting thing.
So you're reading the phrase as
כמו שקץ שיונק? kemo sheket she'yonek?
No, but the infant who is doing it is like the infant
is יונק שקץ. yonek sheket. Meaning we don't sort of, we're not
disapproving of the mother, we think it's disgusting for the child. Right.
Okay, that's what we're saying. Like the child is nursing from an
abomination. Not we're calling the mother an abomination, but more sort of
saying that's disgusting. Like many people say that. Ech, that's disgusting. Three-year-old
nursing from his mother, ech. So whatever, you know, so that's the
first opinion. Wait, let's look at another opinion. The other opinion says,
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, אפילו ארבע וחמש שנים. afilu arba
va'chamisha shanim. No, even four to five years old, he can do
it even much later. Question whether he means literally until five, the
גמרא's Gemara going to, or does he mean as long as you
want? The גמרא's Gemara going to sound like he means five is
somewhat of the upper limit. פירש, peireish, now I will concede, says
Rabbi Yehoshua, that if the child stopped nursing for a while, לאחר
עשרים וארבעה חודש, le'achar esrim ve'arba'ah chodesh, after the twenty-four month cutoff,
וחזר, ve'chazar, then, so once he entered into the normal world of
eating food in a normal way, I shouldn't say that, the world
of eating food like, you know,
whatever, exactly, then to go back to it, then וחזר, ve'chazar, then
it's כיונק שקץ, ke'yonek sheket, then he'll agree that that's disgusting. Okay,
so again, interesting question of what this whole יונק שקץ yonek sheket
is, but like a lot of, you know, it does, it is
a type of an emotional reaction that people have to this. Yes.
The word שקץ sheket and the word תועבה to'eivah are usually both
trans, are generally translated abomination. Yeah, what's the difference?
אוי, oi, well תועבה to'eivah is a,
more specifically, I mean it gets to the whole issue, right, about,
you know, I mean and the whole thing that goes on nowadays
that people says, you know, homosexuality is תועבה, to'eivah, this and that.
תועבה to'eivah also in the Torah applies to, you know, non-seafood and
whatever. תועבה to'eivah seems more that it has to do with a
crossing of what the, what the Torah considers to be a crossing
of boundary lines of categories, of mixing of categories. So therefore, you
know, it's a whole Mary Douglas thing about why certain of the
species are forbidden, because if you have, you know, certain things, like
fish are supposed to swim, so you have something in the ocean
that doesn't swim, you know, it's like a mixed category type of
a thing. So and therefore, you know, if men and women are,
you know, sort of seen as that's the way it sort of
orders society, so a man with a man, it's and so on.
So that has to do with, but it again, it's used for
a wide variety of things whenever there's like a what the, what
the Torah would consider to be a crossing of categories, a mixing
of categories. That's probably the most, you know, specific definition of תועבה.
to'eivah. שקץ, sheket, like שקץ תשקצנו, shaketz teshaktzenu, but there also you
have תועבה, to'eivah, תעב תתעבנו, ta'eiv teta'avenu, so there actually it is
used, okay, but as a verb. know but that but that's more
seen as like something to just like be you know like visceral
recoil from reject you know you know it's abominable and so on.
So that's probably שקץ sheketz is probably more the abomination meaning that
people give it. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara says yeah
it's not intrinsically disgusting it's a framing of boundaries.
Exactly exactly but you do have it as the verb שקץ תשקצנו
ותעב תתעבנו shakeitz teshaktzenu veta'ev teta'avenu so that's anyway alright so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this alright so there you have that
debate how long should a child be nursing.
Again fascinating you like exactly what is the halachic issues here is
this just like a response of what perceived to be appropriate or
not appropriate. So anyway the גמרא Gemara continues אמר מר Amar mar
it's going to look at this מכאן ואילך יונק שקץ mikan ve'eilach
yoneik sheketz afterwards after twenty four months according to the first opinion
it's like you know like nursing
from an abomination or an abominable
act okay ורמינהי ureminhi ask on this יכול יהא חלב מהמהלך על
שתים טמא yachol yehei chalav mehamehalech al shtayim tamei I might think
that milk of humans is not kosher okay ודין הוא vadin hu
and I can make a קל וחומר kal vachomer ומה בהמה שהקלת
במגעה החמרת בחלבה umah behemah sheikaltah bemaga'ah hichmartah bechalavah an animal that
you are lenient when it comes to touching it animals are not
טמא tamei when they're alive you are strict by the milk you
can't eat the milk of non-kosher
animals אדם שהחמרת במגעו adam shehichmartah bemaga'o human being who can be
טמא tamei when he is alive אינו דין שתחמיר בחלבו eino din
shetachmir bechalavo how much more so should you be strict that the
milk should not be kosher of a human being תלמוד לומר את
הגמל Talmud lomar et hagamal do not eat את הגמל et hagamal
and from that את הגמל et hagamal we learn that even the
milk of a camel of a non-kosher animal is also not kosher
כי מעלה גרה היא הוא הוא טמא ki ma'aleh geirah hi hu
hu tamei it is טמא tamei it is the one that the
milk is טמא tamei ואין חלב מהמהלך על שתים טמא אלא טהור
ve'ein chalav mehamehalech al shtayim tamei ela tahor milk of humans is
not טמא tamei it is rather טהור tahor it is kosher to
eat human milk יכול אוציא את החלב שאינו שוה בכל yachol otzi
et hachalav she'eino shaveh bakol maybe I will exclude milk to say
that's kosher because that is not
because that is not consistent meaning that there are milk of some
animals are kosher and some animals are not kosher so I'll say
milk of humans is kosher ולא אוציא את הדם velo otzi et
hadam but I won't exclude the blood of humans שהוא שוה בכל
shehu shaveh bakol which is consistent amongst all all blood of all
animals is not kosher so maybe blood of humans should be not
kosher תלמוד לומר הוא Talmud lomar hu no from the same פסוק
pasuk it by the camel הוא טמא hu tamei only the camel's
טמא tamei ואין דם מהמהלך על שתים טמא אלא טהור ve'ein dam
mehamehalech al shtayim tamei ela tahor not blood of humans again
it's funny how you learn it out from a פסוק pasuk about
a camel and now you learn out both blood and milk so
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot try to figure out exactly where we're
learning it from but that's not our focus the bottom line is
only blood of animals is not kosher only milk of non-kosher animals
is non-kosher blood and milk of humans is not a problem אלא
טהור ela tahor ואמר רב ששת ve'amar Rav Sheshet and רב ששת
Rav Sheshet says אפילו מצות פרישה אין בו afilu mitzvat perishah ein
bo
there's not even a rabbinic mitzva not to eat it so it's
not biblically forbidden it's not rabbinically forbidden so here you see that
milk human milk is not a problem so how could you say
it's יונק שקץ yoneik sheketz and here becomes the difference between the
product and the act of nursing so the גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult הא דפריש הא דלא פריש ha
diparish ha delo parish it's different whether it is separated from the
mother or not human milk itself is not considered to be a
problem halachically and maybe not even some type of a ick disgusting
type of a reaction but the act of nursing is seen as
something that's only appropriate for infants and once somebody is seen out
of the infant category that you know at least the first opinion
after two years the other opinion gives a much longer time but
at a certain stage it's seen to be like you know like
not appropriate to do the act of nursing one minute וחילופו בדם
vechilufa bedam interestingly the reverse is true by blood because by blood
you're not talking about an act of nursing if you were talking
about taking blood directly you know ingesting blood from the body you'd
be talking about like normally you'd hope your own body like you
got a cut and you're going to suck out the blood so
by nursing we say sucking
the milk from the mother is not appropriate after a certain age
but drinking expressed milk is not appropriate by blood we say the
reverse drinking expressed blood drinking like blood outside of a human body
is a problem why because somebody looks at it if somebody looks
at a person drinking expressed milk they think you're drinking milk and
they don't think you're doing anything wrong if somebody looks at somebody
drinking blood that you know was collected in a cup human blood
they'll think it's animal blood okay so you can't drink blood when
it's not when it's been separated from the body but if you
get a cut you can suck your finger because then clearly you're
ingesting human blood and that's not seen as a disgusting act which
is
interesting okay וחילופו בדם vechilufa bedam כדתניא keditanya like we taught in
a ברייתא baraita דם שעל גבי ככר dam she'al gabei kikar if
you have blood that fell on a loaf of bread you were
eating bread and you had a you know your gums were bleeding
then and some blood got on the bread גוררו ואוכלו gorerov ve'ochlo
you scrape it away and then you eat it but you can't
eat the bread with the blood on it because people will might
confuse it with blood of a of an animal. שבין השיניים shebein
hashinayim however while it's between your teeth, it's your gums are bleeding
and it hasn't gone out of your mouth, מוצצו ואינו חושש motzetzo
ve'eino choshesh then you can just like you know suck you know
like ingest it and you don't have to worry or if you
get a cut in your finger you can suck it and you
don't have to worry. Okay, so this is quite interesting, right? But
you understand the difference, right? The difference is that that's just quickly
like you know like ten seconds just you know sucking up the
blood. It's not this whole prolonged act of nursing. But again one
does wonder why is the גמרא Gemara thinking that nursing is appropriate?
Like if somebody would think it's appropriate for someone to be spending
ten minutes sucking the blood out of their finger? Probably not. Probably
it does have something to do with the fact that it's involving
you know the mother's breast and maybe that is seen as somehow
like I don't know like you know an intimate part of the
mother's body and so on and it's another person who's you know
like who's sucking it. It's not the person sucking it from their
own body which is the case by the blood. So fascinatingly we
don't have any problem by expressed milk but we have a problem
from the act of nursing and the exact reverse by the blood.
Surely.
So the הלכה למעשה halakha le-ma'aseh question is there was a chef
in Manhattan five years ago who made some cheese out of his
wife's breast milk and served it to the people in his restaurant.
Oh my god.
So is that so is it כשר kosher or not?
Totally. It's not only is it כשר, kosher, it's not מילכיג. milchig.
Exactly.
Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says okay. That's disgusting.
Yeah. Okay. So okay. By the way interesting issue because תוספות Tosafos
also quotes a ברייתא braisa or I think a what do you
call it a תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim that in addition to saying
that the blood and the milk is non-כשר kosher of a human,
also says that the flesh of a human is not non-כשר. kosher.
And you know there are these cases of course you know that
there's like plane crashes in the middle of nowhere and the survivors
sometimes have to eat the flesh of those that died and you
know then they're like just you know traumatic you know you know
living with that for the rest of their lives. So there are
interesting questions of discussed in הלכה halakha about whether that would technically
be הלכתי halakhically forbidden. You know I mean it might not be
humanly possible and someone to say it's אסור assur because of בל
תשקצו bal tishaktzu it's just an abominable act you know but the
question is is it like as a food non-כשר kosher you know
and you know it's very interesting because human beings are animals you
know you know need to have certain סימנים simanim but human beings
are seen as a separate category so they're never identified as non-כשר
kosher animals and therefore you have technically these types of of rulings
you know in the גמרא. Gemara. So
but there's another also interesting discussion why it says מהלכי שתים mehalechei
shtayim two-legged beasts because presumably this would not be true about you
know I don't know like like a gorilla
although does that really have two legs? Whatever. Anyway but why doesn't
it just say
אדם? adam? So there's some question about that. Some want to say
like maybe the whole disgusting discussion of eating human blood or eating
human meat or whatever or whatever you know you didn't want to
sort of be explicit about that. So you wanted you know maybe
from so you use this more of a euphemism of מהלכי שתים.
mehalechei shtayim. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
מר. Amar mar. רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer אפילו ארבע וחמש
שנים afilu arba ve-hamesh shanim even up to four and five years
old. והתניא Ve-hatanya didn't we teach in a ברייתא braisa רבי יהושע
אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer אפילו חבילתו על כתיפיו afilu chaviloso al ksefav
even if he's got his sack on his back, even if he's
like going to school wearing his knapsack he can still come home
and have lunch with his have lunch with his mother. Exactly. So
the גמרא Gemara says אידי ואידי חד שיעורא הוא. idi ve-idi chad
shiura hu. No, it's the same. He starts wearing a knapsack until
four or five. Of course it doesn't sound like the same אפילו
חבילתו על כתיפיו afilu chaviloso al ksefav doesn't sound like there's an
upper limit right? But the גמרא Gemara here is at least reading
this that he does mean some upper limit. אמר רב יוסף Amar
Rav Yosef הלכה כרבי יהושע halakha ke-Rabbi Yehoshua and we rule that
way. So everybody in the La Leche League is can be very
happy from the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay again what's fascinating
is is that what does it mean to give a הלכתי halakhic
ruling about this? Like what exactly is the איסור? issur? You know
I mean I guess you could say it's a בל תשקצו bal
tishaktzu issue but how do you define what parameters of ew that's
disgusting is, you know? I mean how do you you know anyway
okay. תניא רבי מרינוס Tanya Rabbi Merinus so Rabbi Merinus taught אומר
omer גונח gonei'ach if somebody is like moaning, has some type of
illness, יונק חלב בשבת yonek chalav be-Shabbos he can directly suckle milk
from an animal's udder you know from directly from a cow on
שבת. Shabbos. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason?
יונק Yonek מפרק כלאחר יד mefarek ke-achar yad because to suckle milk
מפרק mefarek the איסור issur of milking is like the איסור issur
of מפרק mefarek which is like דש dash which is like separating
the wheat from the chaff like you know which is removing something
from the from the object if you would in which it grows.
So therefore not that it's connected to the ground that's קוצר kotzer
even after you know after the wheat's been cut you break off
the you know the kernel and you remove the kernel from the
chaff. Similar to like squeezing why can't you squeeze oranges? That's also
דש. dash. So removing the milk from the udder is considered a
type of a דש. dash. So the normal way The normal way
that you do that from a cow is using your hands. To
do it with your mouth is כלאחר יד, K'lachar Yad, is a
שינוי. Shinui. Okay? Is מפרק כלאחר יד, Mefarek K'lachar Yad, ובמקום צערא
U'bimkom Tsara לא גזרו רבנן, Lo Gazru Rabbanan, and in a place
of anguish, of pain, the rabbis did not forbid it. So you're
allowed to go ahead and do this בשינוי. B'shinui. Now, of course,
there's a big question because there's other גמרות Gemarot that sound like
you're not allowed to do a simple שינוי Shinui for צער, Tzar,
normally we sometimes need a double
דרבנן, D'rabbanan, תוספות Tosafot tries to make a distinction between צער Tzar
that's a result of illness as opposed to צער Tzar that's a
result of thirst and discomfort. So there's always this question of what
threshold of, you know, need and pain or whatever do you need
or illness do you need in order to allow one דרבנן D'rabbanan
or only if it's a double דרבנן D'rabbanan and so on. Okay,
but that's basically the גמרא's Gemara answer. That is now, by the
way, one should also point out that the גמרא Gemara doesn't think
that this is יונק שקץ. Yonek Sheketz. Here you have an adult
who's directly suckling from a cow's udder, that's not disgusting. That's just
a שבת Shabbos issue. But for a five-year-old or whatever to nurse
from the mother is disgusting. So again, one does wonder if it
has to do with some perhaps fact about like, you know, this
thing about a mother's breast and once a child gets a certain
age, it's felt as like something sexual. I wonder if that's really
a part of it.
So the גמרא's Gemara assumption is it's an אב מלאכה דאורייתא? Av
Melacha D'oraita? Yep. It is, it uses the language לא גזרו.
Lo Gazru. So תוספות Tosafot has a whole question, well, because it's
כלאחר יד, K'lachar Yad, it's a שינוי, Shinui, so תוספות Tosafot has
also, so let me stop for a moment and say this is
also an extremely important גמרא Gemara in terms of the issue about
a mother expressing milk on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, because the גמרא Gemara
sounds like that to, you know,
to express milk is a דאורייתא. D'oraita. תוספות Tosafot asks the question
and he says one minute, דש, Dash, which this is a part
of דש, Dash, only applies by גידולי קרקע, Gidulei Karka, things that
grow from the ground, human beings don't grow from the ground. So
תוספות Tosafot actually has an opinion that this גמרא Gemara is only
going according to one opinion, but according to maybe the way we
rule, maybe this whole thing would be דרבנן D'rabbanan from the outset
because human beings don't grow from the ground. So it might be
the whole nursing is דרבנן. D'rabbanan. Now expressing milk, here's the question,
for a mother to express milk in a cup, is that a
שינוי? Shinui? Is it the reverse of what you have by a
cow? By a cow the normal way for us as human beings
to get milk out of a cow is milking with the hand.
To directly suckle is a שינוי. Shinui. For human beings, would you
say it's the reverse, the normal way for a mother the milk
to come out is through the infant suckling and to take it
out with the hands is a שינוי? Shinui? So maybe, maybe not,
that seems like a harder point, it seems like, you know, either
way would be considered natural. So does become this whole question of
can you express milk on שבת? Shabbos? So A, can you argue
it's a דרבנן D'rabbanan and B, can you argue like the גמרא
Gemara said before that if the baby really needs it and if
not expressing milk will endanger the baby's milk supply, not like just
סתם Stam you're doing it because, you know,
whatever convenience, there's like a real issue of maybe the baby's milk
supply, then you have the סכנה Sakana argument to
do it.
I, what
I tell women to do ideally if they can is to go
ahead and get an electric pump and put it on a timer,
and therefore hook it up before the like have the timer go
on every hour, every two hours or whatever it is, and hook
it up before the timer goes on. So then when it's already
hooked up and then the timer's going on and then it's just
sort of happening by itself. You're not actively doing any of the
nursing.
There was a case where they weren't able to do that or
whatever, so I said fine, but is there a way you can
use the hands pump with a שינוי? Shinui? We figured it out.
Anyway, but that becomes, that's a very, that's a very common question.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא, Tanya, we
taught a ברייתא, Braita, נחום איש גליא אומר, Nachum Ish Galia Omer,
נחום Nachum from גליא Galia says, צינור, Tzinor,
this is going to be a similar idea of like doing something
when there's a צורך Tzorach on שבת Shabbos and with a ruling
of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. צינור שעלו בו קסקסין, Tzinor She'alu Bo
Kaskasin, if you have a drain pipe that has is filled with
like little, I don't know, like pieces of debris, and therefore what's
happening, the rain is not coming off of the roof and therefore
it's raining through your roof because it's not being drained off. So
ממעכן ברגלו בצנעה בשבת, Memachan B'raglo B'tzina B'shabbos, you can use your
leg to push them down and compress it so the water can
get through because you're doing it with a שינוי Shinui with your
foot, and even though there's a תיקון Tikun element here, nevertheless, ואינו
חושש, V'eino Choshesh, you don't have to worry, מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama,
why? ממעכן
כלאחר יד הוא, Memachan K'lachar Yad Hu, it's an unusual way to
do a תיקון, Tikun, normally you'd use your hands and you'd clean
that with your hands, ובמקום פסידא לא גזרו רבנן, U'bimkom Psida Lo
Gazru Rabbanan, and there's a loss here to the, you know, it'll
ruin your roof. So again, it's interesting and אמר רב יוסף הלכה
כנחום איש גליא זו, Amar Rav Yosef Halacha K'Nachum Ish Galia Zu,
we ruled this way. So it's interesting in both of these cases
as we allow even for for צער tza'ar and פסידא pseda just
one דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Often we need like a double דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So
that's always the question: what threshold of need can allow what type
of a, you know, of an override on שבת Shabbat and different
סוגיות sugyas point in different
ways. פירוש לאחר עשרים וארבעה חודש וחזר, Peirush l'achar esrim v'arba chodesh
v'chazar, if he separated after twenty-four months and then went back, כיונק
שקץ, keyoneh b'sheket, that is like, even if you say you have
to for five years, that if you stopped eating and went back,
stopped nursing and went back, that would be
disgusting. וכמה, V'khama, how much, אמר רב יהודה בר חביבא אמר שמואל
שלשה ימים, amar Rav Yehuda bar Chaviba amar Shmuel shelosha yamim, three
days straight going without nursing. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, תני
tanni that it was a ברייתא, baraita, תני יהודה בר חביבא קמיה
דשמואל שלשה ימים, tanni Yehuda bar Chaviba kamei d'Shmuel shelosha yamim, same
point except a ברייתא. baraita. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught:
מניקת שמת בעלה בתוך עשרים וארבעה חודש. meneket she-met ba'ala b'tokh esrim
v'arba chodesh. So a nurse, a mother who's nursing her child and
the husband dies within twenty-four months. Now what matters if the husband
dies? Because remember, her obligation to nurse the child is only an
obligation to the husband. It's a marital obligation. So the husband died
within twenty-four months, why doesn't she just go ahead and say to
the heirs, "Here, take the kid, take your brother, you know, find
a nursemaid for him, I'm out of here"? So no, we don't
let her do that. Again, like we saw before, you know, she's
got and here, you know, that was a case of divorce anyway,
this is a case of death and maybe she's being supported by
the estate right now. So she has a obligation to ensure that
she'll continue to nurse the child. So what we say is הרי
זו לא תארס ולא תנשא, harei zo lo t'ares v'lo tinasei, don't
get, don't have get קידושין kiddushin and certainly don't get married, don't
get נישואין, nisuin, because then what's going to happen? You will then
get pregnant with this other man and then that will that will
impact your ability to continue to nurse your child. עד עשרים וארבעה
חודש Ad esrim v'arba chodesh for twenty-four months. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rabbi Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir says. Again, what's interesting here is
who's her this obligation to? Is this a case where it's the
infant, מכירה, makkira, recognized the mother? Right? Remember, we had before, if
the infant doesn't recognize the mother, it seems her obligation is only
to the husband. So what where's her obligation now? The husband is
dead. So maybe this is a scenario where the infant recognizes the
mother. There we said we're going to force her to continue to
nurse, okay? But the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell that out. But we
are saying that in a scenario where she is obligated to continue
to nurse the child, she has to make sure that the milk
supply is still good and she can't get even קידושין kiddushin even
though it's not yet נישואין nisuin because we're afraid that it'll eventually
lead to her getting pregnant and compromising the nursing of her child.
Which is interesting because even the תלמוד Talmud knew that it's highly
unlikely for a woman who's nursing actively to get pregnant. Yeah. It's
a natural form of birth control.
It's a good point. It's a good point. That's a very good
point.
There are other גמרות Gemaras I believe I remember correctly that make
that point.
Right, but other גמרות Gemaras say that a מניקת meneket uses birth
control to prevent her from getting pregnant so she doesn't compromise her
milk supply. So that's what this גמרא Gemara is in line with.
But you're right, nursing would usually have the opposite causal effect: not
that the pregnancy will prevent the nursing, the nursing will prevent the
pregnancy. רבי יהודה מתיר בשמונה עשר חודש, Rabbi Yehuda matir b'shmoneh asar
chodesh, and Rabbi Yehuda says once it's already eighteen months, then it's
then, you know, the so this is the opposite end of the
question. The first question was: at what stage is the mother obligated
to continue nursing, do we say the infant recognizes the mother? And
here's the other end: till when is the mother obligated to continue
nursing? Right? We said that a child is allowed to nurse according
to everybody up to twenty-four months. But till when is she obligated?
So here Rabbi Yehuda says only eighteen months. אמר רבי נתן בר
יוסף הן הן דברי בית שמאי הן הן דברי בית הלל, Amar
Rabbi Natan bar Yosef hein hein divrei Beit Shammai hein hein divrei
Beit Hillel, this is the same debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel
בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, שבית שמאי אומרים עשרים וארבעה חודש, she-Beit Shammai
omrim esrim v'arba chodesh, that twenty-four months. Again, remember בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says that a mother does not have a obligation to her
husband to nurse, but here we're saying forget the husband, the obligation
to the child under some circumstances, right? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says that's for twenty-four months has to has to, ובית הלל אומרים,
u-Beit Hillel omrim,
again, maybe this is בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees once the infant
recognizes the mother, because again, remember בית שמאי Beit Shammai said the
mother could take the breast out of the child's mouth. So where's
this obligation? But this might have to do, like I said, a
case where the infant recognizes the mother and then there would be
an obligation. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says twenty-four months, ובית הלל
אומרים שמונה עשר חודש, u-Beit Hillel omrim shmoneh asar chodesh, eighteen months.
אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אני אכריע, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ani akhria, I'll make I'll
compromise, I'll decide. He's not really deciding between בית הלל Beit Hillel
בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, he's really reframing them. לדברי האומר עשרים וארבעה
חודש, L'divrei ha-omer esrim v'arba chodesh, according to the idea of twenty-four
months, מותרת להנשא בעשרים ואחד חודש, muteret l'inasei b'esrim v'echad chodesh, she
can get married at twenty-one months, because it takes because then she
has to get, you know, until she gets married and then she
gets pregnant and until the assumption is the pregnancy is going on
for three months, it doesn't impact the milk supply. So he's not
really מכריע, makhria, he's really reframing that twenty-four months really means twenty-one
months. ולדברי האומר בשמונה עשר חודש, U-l'divrei ha-omer b'shmoneh asar chodesh, and
eighteen months really means מותרת להנשא בחמשה עשר חודש, muteret l'inasei b'chamishah
asar chodesh, she can get married at fifteen months. get married at
15 months. לפי שאין החלב נעכר, Lefi she'ein hachalav ne'echar, the milk
is not sort of like spoiled, אלא אחר שלשה חדשים ella achar
shlosha chadashim
except after three months of pregnancy. Okay, so here's the debate until
when does she have to continue nursing. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, I
guess what, you know, what I find fascinating is why don't they
have the debate that the husband is alive and the mother wants
to stop nursing and the husband wants her to continue nursing. You
could have a just as equal type of a debate of when
is the wife's obligation to the husband, that's where we started, the
wife's obligation to the husband till when does she have to continue
to nurse the child. But this is doing it in a case
where there's no husband and the obligation is more straight to the
child. So how do we rule? And therefore she can't get remarried.
I mean this is framing it not about continuing nursing but framing
it in allowing her to get remarried. So אמר עולא, Amar Ulla,
הלכה כרבי יהודה. Halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like Rabbi Yehuda, 18
months. Is it 18 months at 15 months or 18 months at
18 months, not clear. ואמר מר עוקבא, Ve'amar Mar Ukva, and Mar
Ukva said, לי התיר רבי חנינא, Li hitir Rabbi Chanina, רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina allowed me לישא liseis to marry a woman who I
guess whose husband had died and she had a nursing child and
to marry her לאחר חמשה עשר חודש l'achar chamisha-asar chodesh after 15
months. So it was רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's 18 months then translated
as to 15 months. Okay, רבי חני... Rabbi Chani... now אריסיה דאביי,
Arisey d'Abaye, אביי'ס Abaye's sharecropper, אתא לקמיה דאביי, ata l'kamei d'Abaye, came
to אביי. Abaye. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מהו לארוס בחמשה עשר חודש?
mahu l'areis b'chamisha-asar chodesh? Can I marry a woman whose husband had
died and it's been 15 and and the child has now been
nursing for 15 months? Okay, so that's the same case, right? Child's
been nursing for 15 months, is it okay to get married now
to this woman? אמר ליה, Amar lei, חדא chada number one, דאמר
רבי יהודה הלכה כרבי יהודה, d'amar Rabbi Yehuda halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda, the
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
we always rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says 18 months,
I mean who says 18 not 24 and again assuming 18 means
15. So number one we generally rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
ועוד, Ve'od, בית שמאי ובית הלל, Beis Shammai v'Beis Hillel, if it's
a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel
we're like בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית הלל Beis Hillel also
is the one who says 18 months, which means 15 months. ואמר
עולא, Ve'amar Ulla, so we have those two and עולא Ulla says
הלכה כרבי יהודה Halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda and we rule like him, so
that's three. ואמר מר עוקבא Ve'amar Mar Ukva and מר עוקבא Mar
Ukva says לי התיר רבי חנינא לישא לאחר חמשה עשר חודש. li
hitir Rabbi Chanina liseis l'achar chamisha-asar chodesh. So to me he allowed
15 months. You've got four indications that we rule that you're allowed
after 15 months. So therefore, so כל שכן דאת לארוס, kol sheken
d'at l'areis, certainly you, you at this stage you only want to
do the קידושין, kiddushin, you don't even want to do the נישואין,
nisuin, so it's so obvious, no question of course you can do
it, okay? That's what he said. Now, כי אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף,
ki ata l'kamei d'Rav Yosef, then אביי Abaye went to רב יוסף
Rav Yosef and said hey you know I had this interesting שאלה
shayla today and I told her pshh such an obvious question. So
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said to him you know where you're coming
up for something. אמר ליה, Amar lei, one minute, רב ושמואל דאמרי
תרווייהו צריכה להמתין ארבעה ועשרים חודש חוץ מיום שנולד בו וחוץ מיום
שנתארסה בה, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri duvayu tzricha lehamtin arba'ah ve'esrim chodesh chutz
miyom shenolad bo v'chutz miyom shenisarsah bah, you have to wait 24
months even though you have all those indications of 18 which is
15. We really rule the opposite end of the spectrum, 24 months.
Not only that you don't even you don't count the day the
child is born, you start the clock the next day, and the
day of the קידושין kiddushin has to be the day after the
end of the 24 months, not the day of. So as maximum
as a possible ruling, okay, the opposite extreme. Okay, so רץ בתריה,
ratz basrei, so he ran after the sharecropper to tell him call
off the wedding, תלתא פרסי tlasa parsei three parsangs like three miles
ואמרי לה פרסא בחלא ve'amri lei parsa bechala one say one parsang
but running in sand which is pretty darn hard, ולא אדכיה v'lo
adchei he didn't catch up to him. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי
Abaye said הא מילתא דאמרו רבנן ha milsa d'amru rabnan you know
that thing that the רבנן rabbanan say אפילו כביעתא בכותחא, afilu kebeitza
bekutcha, even whether you're allowed to eat a milk with כותח, kutach,
כותח kutach is a type of a dairy dip, okay so it's
actually a classic discussion by פסח Pesach about a dairy dip that
had breadcrumbs in it and so on, okay so even the question
of eating an egg with with a dairy dip, לא לישרי איניש
במקום רביה, lo lishri inish bemakom rabei, don't פסק'ן pasken and say
oh it's מותר, muttar, it's so obvious it's מותר muttar like sometimes
that's the phrase in the גמרא Gemara כביעתא בכותחא kebeitza bekutcha like
it's so obvious like can you eat eggs with milk? Okay so
don't פסק'ן pasken that if it's the place of your רבי, Rebbi,
if you're in the you know the the city of your רבי,
Rebbi, the town of your רבי, Rebbi, לא משום דמחזי כאפקירותא, lo
mishum demichzi ke'apikorusa, not because it seems חוצפה'דיק, chutzpadik, you know in
you know disrespectful, if it was just an issue of disrespectful you
should be allowed if your רבי Rebbi allows you to do it,
אלא משום דלא מסתיימא מילתא, ella mishum delo mistayeim milsa, it's you
don't you won't have you know the help you won't be have
this sort of divine help you know it won't succeed meaning the
you know you don't get that sort of you know sort of
heavenly support in your פסק, psak, למימרא l'memra to say it correctly,
you know if you're in the place of your רבי Rebbi then
your רבי Rebbi is the one you know then then you maybe
somehow it's inappropriate I it's funny it's like not disrespectful but why
is it not מסתיימא מילתא mistayeim milsa if it's not disrespecting? But
somehow in an objective sense if your רבי'ס Rebbi's around even if
he's not מקפיד makpid he should be פסק'ן-ing pasken so you won't
get that heavenly support to פסק'ן pasken correctly. Okay. דהא אנא הוה
גמירנא ליה להא דרב ושמואל. Deha ana hava gmirna leh l'hade d'Rav
u'Shmuel. I actually knew the ruling of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
that said you had to wait twenty four months and nevertheless אפילו
הכי לא מסתייעא לי מילתא למימר afilu hachi lo mistaia li miltha
l'meimar I didn't it wasn't aided presumably by heaven in order to
say it meaning I forgot it, it slipped my mind. So you
see that if you're in the place of your רבי Rebbe you
should refer all שאלות shailos to your רבי Rebbe even if your
רבי Rebbe allows you to פסקן. pasken. Okay. That's very interesting psychologically.
In other words the guy's like he's big sort of he's feeling
good about himself, right, totally confident but there's a type of it's
like an ambition, right, even though my רבי's Rebbe in the same
place like I can handle this right right right and and you
get sloppy. Yeah, that's interesting. Right. Or could be impetuous, there's a
little bit of impetuousness. That's an interesting point, right, to say to
say oh yeah I can do this right right right so your
ego you're right. But it is quite fascinating though also thank you
that's very helpful but it is quite fascinating that so what you
got רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. It seems like you got a
pretty strong lineup on the other side, you know. Anyway, alright. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. And it was only ארוסין, erusin, it wasn't even
נישואין. nisuin. Anyway, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. נתנה בנה למניקת natna bnah
l'menekes if she gave the child over to a nursemaid או גמלתו
o gemalto or she weaned him או מת o mes or the
child died מותרת להינשא מיד mutteres l'hinnase miyad then she can get
married because then the child's taken care of or there's no child.
רב פפא Rav Pappa ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע v'Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yehoshua סברו למעבד עובדא כי הא מתניתא savru l'me'avad uvda ki
ha matnisa they wanted to rule like this ברייתא. braisa. אמרה להו
ההיא סבתא amra lehu hahi savta a certain elderly woman said to
them בדידי הוה עובדא bididi hava uvda you know this case happened
with me ואסר לי רב נחמן v'asar li Rav Nachman and רב
נחמן Rav Nachman forbade me even though I satisfied one of these
criteria he still said I had to wait the twenty four months.
So איני eini is this really true? והא רב נחמן שרא להו
לבי ריש גלותא veha Rav Nachman shara lehu l'vei Resh Galusa רב
נחמן Rav Nachman allowed the women of the house of the ריש
גלותא Resh Galusa to get married at an earlier stage once they
had weaned their child or something. So the גמרא Gemara said ah
or gave it to a nursemaid גמרא Gemara said שני בי ריש
גלותא דלא הדרו בהו. shani bei Resh Galusa d'lo hadru behu. No,
in the house of ריש גלותא Resh Galusa it's different they won't
reverse themselves. Once they're married you know the ריש גלותא Resh Galusa
were some strong men and so on so the wives are not
going to now change their minds the husbands aren't going to let
them. Oh I want to take my child back I regret giving
him to the nursemaid you know no they're not you know the
husband their new husbands are going to prevent that from happening. Okay
so apparently these were women who were married to other men being
who whose husbands died who married into בי ריש גלותא bei Resh
Galusa and that's not going to reverse but another woman we're afraid
she might change her mind and therefore we want to wait out
the whole twenty four months okay. Of course the changing mind is
only likely in the case of in the case of a nursemaid
I suppose if even after a child is weaned in theory you
could resume it okay but anyway but not in the case of
died what's the concern? So that's what the גמרא Gemara will get
to. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר להו רב פפי
amar lehu Rav Pappi so רב פפי Rav Pappi said אטון לא
תשמעו מהא דתניא attun lo sishme'u meha d'tanya one minute why did
you need the test you know how why did you need this
woman to tell you that we don't rule that way wouldn't you
have known it from that which we taught in the ברייתא? braisa?
הרי שהייתה רדופה לילך לבית אביה harei she-hayesa redufa leilech l'veis aviha
let's say there's a woman who can assume is not having sex
with her husband. What's the case? She's always running to her father's
house you know maybe she's a whole twelve and a half years
old
okay so she's basically spending all the time in
her father's house she's not spending any time in her husband's house
או שהיה לה כעס בבית בעלה o she-haya lah ka'as b'veis ba'alah
or clear that they were you know there's a lot of marital
discord או שהיה בעלה חבוש בבית האסורין o she-haya ba'alah chavush b'veis
ha-asurin or he's in prison או שהלך בעלה למדינת הים o she-halach
ba'alah l'medinas ha-yam or he's off in China או שהיה בעלה זקן
או חולה o she-haya ba'alah zaken o choleh or he's elderly or
ill infirm או שהייתה היא עקרה וזקנה ואילונית וקטנה o she-hayesa hi
akara u'zkena v'aylonis u'ketana or she is a sterile or she's elderly
or she was never able to have children or she was a
minor and can't have children והפילה אחר מיתת בעלה v'hipila achar misas
ba'alah or a woman who miscarried after her husband died in all
these cases we know she's not pregnant either we assume she's never
been hasn't been having sex or in some of the latter cases
even if she's been having sex we know she's not pregnant so
in all these cases ושאינה ראויה לילד v'she'eina re'uya leiled or just
a woman who is not able to give birth it's a little
unclear how that's different than עקרה akara anyway in all these cases
כולן צריכות להמתין שלושה חודשים kullan tzrichos l'hamtin shelosha chodashim they all
have to wait three months דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Now
this is not about the issue about the milking and the nursing
of the child this is a different issue this is an issue
about getting remarried because you don't want that that the woman gets
remarried gets pregnant right away and you don't know if this child
who the father is so this is the waiting of three months
between one marriage and the next in order to ensure who the
father you know you know who the father is. So as opposed
to before twenty four months eighteen months that was with a child
this is just three months to know who the father is but
the case is what if you have a particular scenario that you
have no concern that you know for sure she hasn't been having
sex and she's not pregnant? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir still says we
don't make distinctions she still has to wait three months ורבי יוסי
מתיר לינשא מיד v'Rabbi Yosi mattir l'hinnase miyad and רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi allows it right away now how do we rule? ואמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי מאיר בגזירותיו v'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel
halacha k'Rabbi Meir bi-gzeirosav we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who's
being sort of like consistent. and categorical and we never allow it.
So if we don't allow her to remarry when we know she's
not pregnant until she waits three months, we shouldn't allow her to
remarry before the 24 months even if we know she's not pregnant,
even if she's weaned the child or you know other types of
things, we should take a לא פלוג lo plug approach and say
we always demand 24 months even if the child no longer will
be nursing. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר להו לאו אדעתאי,
Amar lehu lav ada'ata'i, I'm sorry, says you're right, I wasn't thinking,
but the same way we always rule three months for remarriage by
the case of no child, we should always rule 24 months by
the case of child even in the scenario where we're not concerned
that he might be, that she might resume to nurse the child.
And what's the הלכה? halakha? והלכתא והלכה היא מת, V'hilkheta v'halakha hi
met, here's the one scenario we will allow. If the child died,
okay, then there's nothing to be concerned about, okay, then מותר, mutar,
then she can get remarried within the 24 months. גמלתהו, Gemalathu, if
she weaned him, אסור, asur, because then we're afraid that weaning will
lead to a case of non-weaning or maybe even after being weaned
he'll return, so we have to wait 24 months except for the
case of child has died. Any other case even if he's been
given over to a nursemaid, even if he's been weaned, we say
you still have to wait the 24 months. So now the גמרא
Gemara just to end this, מר בר רב אשי אמר אפילו מת
נמי אסור. Mar bar Rav Ashi amar afilu met nami asur. Even
if the child has died, you cannot, she cannot remarry within 24
months, why? This is very horrific. דילמא קטלה ליה, dilma katla lei,
we're afraid that she'll be so eager to remarry, I mean, you
know, maybe women are so, you know, need in terms of their,
you know, protection, that, you know, and they so eager that she'll
kill her infant child ואזלא ומינסבא v'azla u'minsva in order to remarry.
So הוה עובדא וחנקתיה havah uvda v'chanaktia and actually there was a
story where this turned out, I mean, there are stories of, you
know, mothers who kill their children, you know, so therefore, that she
strangled her child. So therefore we cannot allow this case to be
a קולא kula because God forbid what it would lead to. So
the גמרא Gemara though says ולא היא, v'lo hi, but that's not
true. ההיא שוטה הות, Hahi shota havah, that woman was crazy. When
you hear cases of mothers who kill their children, usually it is
because they have some mental illness. ולא עבדי אינשי דחנקי בנייהו, V'lo
avdi inshi d'chanki b'naihu, we do not have to be concerned that
women will kill their own children. So therefore the one case we
can allow is the case of מת met for the infant to
get remarried within 24 months. By the way, the interesting question about
getting remarried within three months, it also happens if a woman converts,
do we allow her and she converts with her husband, do we
allow them to continue living together, do we wait three months in
order to know whether the child was conceived before she converted, after
she converted? Anyway, there's a number of פוסקים poskim that allow pregnancy
tests. So on the one hand, even though the גמרא Gemara says
it sounds like you had a very clear לא פלוג lo plug
approach, some would do say that a pregnancy, some there are those
that will allow pregnancy tests and say that that will be different
than the cases in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, I will see you
all on פסח. Pesach.